Have you considered, John?
你考虑过了吗 约翰?
Aye.
是的
Your answer?
答案是?
No.
不
Why, pray?
敢问为何?
You would have me sit as a judge at the King's trial.
你要我做裁审员 出席对国王的审判
Others have already agreed.
别人都同意了
By whose authority will he be tried?
依谁的权力审判他?
By that of Parliament.
议会的权力
Oliver!
奥利佛
This is your Parliament, since you purged it.
大清洗后这便是你的议会了
Is that not the truth?
我说的不是事实吗?
Aye, sir, for you are Honest John Lilburne.
没错 先生 你是正直的约翰·李尔本嘛
Let a new Parliament be freely elected,
自由选举新议会
let that Parliament call for the King...
然后再审判国王...
We waste our breath together, sir.
我们这是在浪费口舌 先生
Then answer me this one thing
那回答我一件事
if it happen that Charles Stuart be found innocent of the crime
如果结果查尔斯·斯图尔特的反人民罪
of making war on his people,
被判无罪
will you let him be set free?
你会放过他吗?
England will be never be at peace
英格兰将永无宁日
till this matter of the King be settled once for all.
除非处决国王 一了百了
Fare you well.
告辞了
Newgate Prison London
伦敦纽杰特监狱
Just one more time.
再来一次
You're nearly there. Again. And breath and push...
就快好了 再来一次 呼吸向外推...
Hard, hard! Push, Angelica, push!
用力 用力 推 安吉丽卡 向外推
Yes, yes!
好了 好了
翻译：Tpring 奈利 多切 麦麦
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
The court commands the charge be read.
法庭允许宣读申诉
My Lord, in behalf of the Commons of England
大人 我谨代表英格兰议会
and of all the people thereof...
及其全体人民...
Hold a little.
等一下
In behalf of the Commons of England
谨代表英格兰议会
and of all the people thereof,
及其全体人民
I do accuse Charles Stuart, here present,
控告查尔斯·斯图尔特如下罪行
as a tyrant, traitor and murderer,
专制暴政 叛国 谋杀
public and implacable enemy to the Commonwealth of England
他是全体英格兰人民不可饶恕的公敌
and man of blood!
一个嗜血成性之徒
God save the King! God save the King!
上帝拯救国王 上帝拯救国王
God save the King!
上帝拯救国王
Sir, we would have your answer.
先生 我们愿闻您的申辩
I would know by what lawful authority I am called hither.
我愿知是何法律效力将我传唤于此
Remember, I am your King.
记住 我是你们的国王
We are satisfied of our own authority.
我们由自己统治足矣
It is not your self-satisfaction that should decide the matter.
这不是你们自我满足就能裁决的事
I know as much law as any one of you.
我比你们任何人都熟知法典
Show me one precedent in history for these proceedings.
告诉我一个历史上此等诉讼的先例
It is not for a prisoner to require.
这不是一个犯人该提的要求
Sir, I am not an ordinary prisoner.
阁下 我不是普通的犯人
Make them be quiet!
让他们肃静
Clear the court!
清理法庭
A boy. He came too early into the world - no air in his lungs.
是个男孩 他早产太久 没有呼吸了
Now the law can hang me.
现在依法可以绞死我了
Ask Elizabeth to fetch me my wedding dress
请伊丽莎白把我的结婚礼服拿来
and then you can go home, Saxby.
然后你就可以回家了 塞斯比
I have no home, if you be hanged.
如果你被绞死 我便无家可归了
Then wander the world,
那就云游四海去吧
for hanged I must be.
我必然会被绞死
You're guilty!
你有罪
Murderer!
杀手
King of Blood! There's blood on your hands!
嗜血国王 你双手沾满鲜血
In the name of the people of England...
以英格兰人民之名...
Not a half! Not a quarter of the people of England!
不到一半 连四分之一英格兰人都不到
Oliver Cromwell is a traitor!
奥利佛·克伦威尔是叛徒
Oliver Cromwell is a traitor!        Away!
奥利佛·克伦威尔是叛徒      快滚
The prisoner, having refused to give his answer to the charges
犯人拒绝对其控告做出申辩
has thereby confessed his guilt.
藉此认定他承认了罪行
The prisoner may speak.
犯人还有什么要说的
I must tell you all...
我必须告诉你们
..this many a day, all things have been taken away from me...
这些日子来 我身边所有的东西都被夺走
..but that which I call more dear to me than my life...
除了那些我看作比生命更珍贵的东西
..my conscience
我的良心
and my honour.
和我的荣誉
If I had more respect to my life
如果我珍惜自己的生命
than the peace of the kingdom...
更甚于王国的和平
..I should've made a defence for myself
我会为自己辩驳
that might leastwise have delayed the ugly sentence
那也许至少能延迟你们
which I believe you will pass on me.
就要宣布的这丑陋的判决
I know it is in vain to dispute with you.
我知道同你们争论是徒劳的
I cannot deny the power you have.
我反抗不了你们的权力
I have nothing more to say.
我没有要说的了
Sir, there is a bond made between a king and his people.
先生 国王和他的人民之间有一道契约
A bond of protection due from the sovereign
一道由君主的保护
and subjection due from the people.
和子民的隶从组成的契约
When this bond is once broken...
一旦契约被破坏...
..farewell sovereignty.
君权便不复存在
Charles Stuart, as a tyrant, traitor,
查尔斯·斯图尔特 作为暴君 叛国者
murderer and a public enemy,
谋杀犯 人民公敌
shall be put to death
将被处死
by the severing of his head from his body.
行刑斩首
Why is it so still?
怎么这么安静?
They kill the King today.
他们今天处死国王
Where are your friends today, madam?
你的朋友在哪 夫人?
Here before me, sirrah
就在我面前 老小子
ready to pull at my legs and hasten my death.
等着拖住我的双腿好让我死得痛快些
Where's the hangman?
刽子手在哪?
Elizabeth, tell your mother when you see her
伊丽莎白 看见你母后时告诉她
that my thoughts have never strayed from her,
我的心从没有离开她
that my love will be the same to the last. Will you tell her?
我的爱将永恒不变 你会告诉她吗?
Sweetheart, I fear you will forget this.
宝贝 我怕你会忘了
I shall never forget it whilst I live.
今生今世我都不会忘记
Child...
孩子
..they will cut off my head...
他们要砍掉我的头...
..and perhaps make you a King.
也许会让你做国王
But mark what I say...
不过牢记我说的
You must not be a king so long as your brothers do live.
只要你的兄长还活着 你就不能做国王
I'll be torn in pieces first.
我宁可被五马分尸
It is very low.
这太低了
It can be no higher, sir.
不能再高了 先生
Remember.
牢记
You die a thief, a murderess and a whore.
你作为一个小偷 杀手 妓女被处死
Will you at last admit your guilt and beg forgiveness?
你愿最终承认自己的罪行 并乞求宽恕吗?
I will beg nothing from you,
我不会向你乞求任何东西
nor any man.
不向任何人乞求
Men have accused me,
那些控告我的人
men have judged me...
那些裁判我的人...
..and now men will kill me.
还有现在杀死我的人
Men have sought to silence me all my days.
那些企图让我一直保持沉默的人
But, before I am cut off, hear me.
但在我死前 听我说
You're the thief, sir, for that you've stolen this world.
你才是小偷 先生 是你洗劫了这个世界
You're the murderer, for that you've killed its dreams.
你才是凶手 是你扼杀了一切梦想
And you, sir, are the whore,
你 先生 才是妓女
for you sold your soul for a bag of gold.
只为一袋金币便出卖了自己的灵魂
Very pretty gallows speech.
很出色的临刑演说
Where is the hangman?
刽子手在哪?
Make haste, sir
快点 先生
my master has bought a window at Whitehall.
我主人在白厅买了一个窗位
On another day,
要是在别的日子
I could have wished her your slowest death.
我会希望你慢慢死去
Hangman, I forgive you.
刽子手 我宽恕你
But today,
但是今天
hurry, sir.
快点 先生
No more words, madam?
没什么要说的了 夫人?
Where is Colonel Rainsborough today, hmm?
今天雷恩巴勒上校在哪 嗯?
What?
什么?
You cannot speak?
你说不出话了?
Are her ankles not pretty?
她的脚踝不美吗?
Let me pull on her legs!
让我拖着她的腿
No.
不
For pity's sake!
发发善心吧
We lose time, sir.
我们没时间了 先生
Hangman, do not bring her down until she be dead.
刽子手 她不咽气就不许放下来
We must leave now, sir.
我们得赶快走了 先生
On, sir.
走吧
Edward!
爱德华
Stay for the sign.
等我示意再砍
Breathe!
呼吸啊
Order! Stand back!
肃静 退回去
You should scares spesk to Cramwel about everything now,
如今大家见到克伦威尔都不敢作声了
but he will lay his hand upon his breast.
可他还会用手按着心口
Aye and he'll elevate his eyes. He'll call God to record.
对 他会抬眼望苍天 以上帝作见证
He will weep, he will howl, he will repent.
他会流泪 他会哭号 他会忏悔
Even while he doth smite you under the fifth rib!
同时却狠狠地当胸给你一拳
Comrades, what did the army fight for, eh?
朋友们 军队是为何而战?
To make Oliver absolute lord and ruler over Ireland...
是为了让奥利佛在爱尔兰成为最高统治者
..As he is now, over England.
就像他现在统治英格兰一样
England's new chains, England's new chains!
英格兰的新枷锁 英格兰的新枷锁
Read it and weep!
读读吧 哭泣吧
Gentlemen.
先生们
Edward.
爱德华
The republic fights for its first breaths while Honest John
共和国还在为迎接诞生的一刻而挣扎
incites the army to mutiny against me.
而正直的约翰却在煽动军队造反
Is this how he sees me now Edward?
他现在就是这么看我吗? 爱德华
As a tyrant?
当我是个暴君?
You may speak openly. Master Thurloe serves the nation.
你可以直言 图尔洛先生是效忠国家的人
Freeborn John thinks he may have seen your hand at work
自由人约翰觉得你有可能一手操控了
in the murder of Thomas Rainsborough.
托马斯·雷恩巴勒的死
Do the Leveller regiments talk of that?
平等派军团也这么说吗?
In secret. For there is hardly a one now in England
只在背地里 现在的英国很难找到
does not fear the General.
一个不害怕将军的人
And you?
那你呢?
Did you see my hand in it?
你觉得是我操控的吗?
No.
不
Then will you come with me?
那你会跟我一起去吗?
To Ireland.
去爱尔兰
To kill Papists?
去杀天主教徒吗?
To make certain that no Scottish or French armies
去确保苏格兰和法国军队
will ever find friends there.
无法在那里找到同谋
My army is brave but they will see sights in Ireland
我的军队是勇敢的 但他们也许尚未做好准备
that they never thought to see.
目睹即将在爱尔兰发生的场面
I need eyes with me there, who have seen those sights before.
我需要目睹过这种场面的人跟我一起去
Your army is owed its wages.
你的军队已经在欠饷了
As we take the land from the Papists,
我们从天主教徒那里夺得土地
we will sell it to Protestants,and pay the army its wages.
卖给新教徒 然后给军队发饷
And what of the Papists?
那天主教徒们怎么办?
When last they arose
上次他们暴乱时
they killed mothers and ate their babies, sir.
残杀妇女生吃婴儿 先生
They are beyond humanity, Edward. Come with me.
他们毫无人性 爱德华 跟我去吧
The man who stood so close to Thomas Rainsborough,
那个站在托马斯·雷恩巴勒一边的人
must now stand close to me.
现在必须要跟我站在一边
Come, sir. Will you be Colonel Sexby?
先生 你原意担任塞斯比上校吗?
Brighten your sword, Colonel Sexby.
擦亮你的宝剑 塞斯比上校
The Lord has work for us both.
上帝赋予了你我使命
You must first to Burford, Edward.
你首先要去博福德 爱德华
The Leveller regiments have arrested their officers
平等派军团把他们的军官都抓了起来
and refuse to march for Ireland.
他们不愿进军爱尔兰
Honest John has his mutiny.
正直的约翰煽动叛乱成功了
Mutiny?
叛乱?
These are brave and honest men, sir. I know them.
这些都是最忠勇不过的人 先生 我了解他们
Go to them as from me. Let them lay down their arms
代表我去找他们 让他们放下武器
and release their officers.
把军官们都放了
Tell them Old Noll will come to them in person
告诉他们老奥利佛将亲自去见他们
and all their grievances will be heard, upon my word.
倾听他们的冤情 我保证
What are your plans, madam?
你打算怎么办 夫人?
To live the life you gave me.
珍惜你给予我的生命
What will you do?
你打算怎么办?
I go to Ireland. I have an officer's wages.
我要去爱尔兰 我可以领到军官的俸禄
They are yours.
都归你所有
How?!
为什么?
Be my wife.
嫁给我
I promised the best man in England I would protect you.
我向英格兰最好的男人承诺过我会保护你
Be my wife, in outward show only and my promise is kept.
做我的妻子 仅仅是名义上的 我会信守承诺
A woman cannot survive alone.
一个单身女人是无法存活的
No, Sexby...
不 塞斯比
I mean to shift for myself now.
我想转换一种生活
There are Diggers at Fanshawe House.
在范肖老宅有一群掘地者(激进平等派)
I mean to join them.
我想去加入他们
The Diggers follow Thomas' dreams
掘地者追求着托马斯的理想
Land a commonwealth, property levelled
土地共有 财产平分
and every man's conscience his own.
所有人都自给自足
The Diggers will not take you in if you be unmarried.
如果你单身 掘地者是不会接收你的
Consider.
考虑一下吧
I do not ask for love.
我不祈求有爱情
I do not ask for...
我不祈求有...
a marriage bed.
同床共眠
I ask only that you let me serve you.
我只祈求你 让我服侍你
Would you have me write you letters?
你想让我给你写信吗?
Sexby...
塞斯比
Why have you done this?
你为什么这么做?
Duty, madam.
为了责任 夫人
A promise given.
我作出过承诺
Freeborn John writes us this message from the Tower.
自由的约翰从牢里给我们写了这些话
"If Cromwell is allowed to go on as he is,
"如果放任克伦威尔为所欲为"
"he will make himself King
"他将立他自己为王"
"and there will be nothing but cutting of throats, year..."
"到那时就只剩肆无忌惮的杀戮了"
Make way for Colonel Sexby!
给塞斯比上校让条路
This you may not do and still be soldiers.
士兵是不允许作出这种行为的
Untie your officers. This defiance cannot go on.
把军官们解开 不能再这样挑衅下去了
Give them their weapons and their horses.
把他们的战马和武器还给他们
Be not afraid of them hereafter.
但从今往后无需再惧怕他们
One greater than them comes to listen to you.
更伟大的人会来倾听你们的诉求
The General himself.
将军本人
Now hear me. Throw your weapons up here.
现在听我说 把你们的武器丢到这里
Do it now.
现在就丢
Nay! Never!
不 永远别想
Come now.
来吧
Let none say you drew your weapons at Old Noll.
不要让人说你们把武器对准老奥利佛
When you speak, he will listen.
你们说话时 他会倾听
When he speaks, you will listen.
他说话时 你们也要倾听
He will give you orders and you will obey them.
他会给你们下命令 你们会执行
There will be no reprisals.
不必担心有报复
This he has promised me and I promise you the same.
这是他给我的承诺 而我则给你们同样的承诺
In the name of Thomas Rainsborough.
以托马斯·雷恩巴勒的名义
Rainsborough! Rainsborough!
雷恩巴勒 雷恩巴勒
General!
将军
You thought to mutiny?
你们要叛变是吗?
You thought to imprison your officers?
你们要把你们的军官关起来是吗?
You thought to give orders to the Army Council?
你们打算对军事议会发号施令吗?
Show me the ringleaders.
把造反头目给我指出来
They will face a court martial immediately.
他们将立刻受到军事法庭的审判
Sir!
先生
Your part is played, Colonel.
你的任务已经完成了 上校
Fire!
开枪
You kept no covenant with us.
你没有兑现给我们的承诺
Is there is anyone who will not willingly submit to my will
还有人不愿意听命于我
and accept my pardon?
接受我的宽恕吗?
Do you wish to resign your commission, Edward?
你是想辞去你的委任吗 爱德华?
Ireland is our back door. It must be bolted.
爱尔兰是我们的后大门 必须要栓牢
We march for Ireland.
我们向爱尔兰进军
Thomas Rainsborough
托马斯·雷恩巴勒（1640-1648）
Why keep that one?
为什么保留了这一座?
Why this one?
为什么?
Thomas Rainsborough lies there.
托马斯·雷恩巴勒安息于此
Should be at the head of England.
他本应是英格兰的领袖的
What's your business here, madam?
你来这里干什么呢 夫人?
I come to dig, if you will let me.
我来种地的 如果你们愿意收我
Your name?
你叫什么名字
Sexby.
塞斯比
Mistress Sexby.
塞斯比夫人
Your husband?
你丈夫呢?
Gone from me.
他离我而去了
Dead?
过世了?
Not dead.
没有过世
Gone to Ireland.
去了爱尔兰
Come with me, Mistress Sexby.
跟我来吧 塞斯比夫人
Mistress Sexby wishes to live among us.
塞斯比夫人想跟我们一起生活
Her husband is fighting in Ireland.
她丈夫在爱尔兰作战
You are welcome, Mistress Sexby.
欢迎你 塞斯比夫人
Those who work, eat. We share all.
劳动便有饭吃 我们分享一切
Your story is written in your hands.
你的人生写在你手掌上了
I think you were not born to this work.
我看你不是干这个出身的
My name is Christian.
我叫克里斯廷
Tell me about the man in the earth whose grave you tend.
给我讲讲你看的那座坟墓里埋着的人
I never knew him but by report.
我对他只有些耳闻
He raised up the common man.
他让平民揭竿而起
He fought for his liberty against the rich...and mighty.
为了自由 他对抗富人...还有贵人
Truly, I wish he was here.
我真希望他能在这里
Wishing will not bring him.
希望不会让他返生
Nay but he should be here,
不会 可他应该在这
for we are living in the best and last of days.
因为我们生活在最好的时代 最后的时代
Our last days are near?
最后审判日临近了?
Christ is ready to walk the earth again.
基督已准备好再临人间
Do you not feel his love all around you?
你不觉得他的爱无处不在吗?
Christ Jesus has come to me.
耶稣基督对我显灵了
Tell us what you saw, Jocelyn.
说说你看见了什么 乔瑟琳
He came down last night and lay by me in my bed.
他昨晚降临人世 躺在我身边
told me he would come soon
告诉我他很快就会回来
and rain upon the earth 10,000 years.
保我们风调雨顺一万年(约伯记 5:10)
Shall we pray, Mistress Sexby?
我们祈祷吧 塞斯比夫人?
Oh, mighty God, who throughout the mouths of babes
全能的主啊 您借幼儿
and sucklings have ordained strength
和婴孩之口赐我们力量
and make of infants to glorify thy name with their innocence.
以他们的无邪显示您的无上荣耀
Inspire us with thy grace...
请以您的仁慈激励我们...
Another sign.
又一个神迹
Come.
来吧
We begin again.
我们从头再来
Colonel, did your party reach Wexford?
上校 你们到达诺克斯福德了吗?
We were held a while at Arklow, General.
我们在沃克洛耽误了一阵 将军
It must be removed from our path.
必须除掉这块绊脚石
It is done. The garrison fled.
已经除掉了 驻军逃跑了
What's left has been driven into a bog.
剩下的都赶进了沼泽里
There they wait for you.
他们在那等您
Is this the flower of all their army?
这就是他们部队的精锐?
Bring them out.
把他们带出来
They are stuck fast.
他们坚守不动
How many are they?
多少人?
Twelve.
12个
Twelve bullets then. We're short on powder and shot.
那就是12颗子弹了 我们军火短缺
Make ready the cannon!
准备大炮
Are you ready to surrender, sir?
您准备投降了吗 先生?
Resist and you will blow you all to atoms.
顽抗就把你们全炸成齑粉
I cannot.
我不能
Surrender and you live.
投降就赦你们不死
Resist and your entire garrison will be put to the sword
顽抗的话 你手下所有人都会被杀
man and boy
无论长幼
I may not.
我不愿意
He has orders.
他有命令
He will not defend the town purposefully
他不会真的誓死捍卫城镇
but needs to make a show of a fight before he surrenders.
但投降前要作出抵抗的样子
Purposeful or no, they will die, all of them.
真也好假也好 他们全都在劫难逃了
I'll drag no prisoners across this benighted land.
在这片愚昧的土地上 我不留俘虏
Wake me when the walls are breached.
城破再叫醒我
Prepare to die.
准备去死吧
Ready?
准备就绪?
Fire the cannon!
开炮
Edward!
爱德华
I hate to see any man's resting place neglected.
我不愿看到任何人的安息之地荒芜
Let me help you.
让我来帮你
Harry Fanshawe.
哈里·范肖
I wonder what he was?
不知他是何等样人?
Your words moved me, sir.
你的话打动了我 先生
When you said these days were like the days of Christ on earth.
你说如今就如同基督在世
Full of love.
到处充满爱
I feel that love in these good people's hearts.
我能感到这些好人们心中的爱
They are good people.
他们确实是好人
But they know not the intenseness of the times.
可他们不了解时局的紧张
But I believe that you do.
可我相信你了解
I believe that you taste
我相信你能体会
the rare and beautiful air that we breathe.
我们呼吸的空气何等珍贵而甘美
I have a sin to confess.
我有项罪行要忏悔
I am no priest, sir.
我不是牧师 先生
When I thought I heard you say that your husband was dead...
当我听到您说您丈夫离你而去时
..my heart was glad.
我顿感欣慰
He lives...still.
他...尚在人间
Though he be far away.
虽然远在天涯
Goodnight.
晚安
Both your husbands are dead, madam.
您的两位丈夫都死了
And lie here at my feet.
就躺在我脚下
I will tell no other.
我不会声张
For truly I think this
因为我真的觉得
the bravest and best thing that any woman ever did.
您是最勇敢最出色的女子
How do you know me?
你怎么认识我?
My mother worked in your kitchens.
我母亲在您的厨房干活
They hanged me as The Devil's Whore.
他们以"魔鬼的妓女"为名绞死了我
Then I love the Devil's whore,
那么我爱上了魔鬼的妓女
for truly I could never love my lady Angelica Fanshawe.
因为我绝不可能爱上我的主母安吉丽卡·范肖
She is far above me.
她与我相隔云泥
Though I would give my life for her.
尽管我愿意为她献出生命
Be not so eager to give your life, Christian.
不要这么热衷于献出生命 克里斯廷
You may not be given another, as I was.
你不像我 不会有第二条命了
Come.
来吧
The owner of the land will never let us be.
这片土地的主人不肯放过我们
Master Joliffe is not the true owner of the land.
若利夫先生不是这里的主人
We are the owners of the land
我们才是这片土地的主人
for we work the land and we make it fruitful.
我们在这里劳作 让它结出硕果
Master Joliffe?
若利夫先生?
Aye, given it by Parliament.
对 国会给他的
These things began when she came.
她来之后才有了这种事
You think I brought these things upon you?
你觉得是我把这些带给你们的?
The Devil's work began when you came among us,
自从你来到我们中间 魔鬼就纠缠不休
with his mark upon your neck. That is all.
你颈上有他的印记 就是这样
They are frightened.
他们害怕了
I will leave tomorrow.
我明天就走
I will follow you to the end of the earth.
我会追随你到世界尽头
Christian...?
克里斯廷?
It is our desire, madam, that you leave us.
我们都希望 夫人 您能离开
You have your wish,
就如你们所愿吧
even though this life here
尽管这里的生活
began to light a candle of hope in my heart.
已经为我点亮了一盏心灯
We will not have fornicators!
我们不要通奸犯
I saw them.
我看见他们了
She saw nothing. The child imagines things.
她什么也没看见 小孩子胡思乱想罢了
I see the Devil at her side.
我看见魔鬼站在她身边
She gave Satan her baby.
她把亲生孩子献给了撒旦
In God's name, make an end of this.
看在上帝份上 适可而止吧
No, sir, we will make an end of you and this woman,
不 先生 我们要了结的是你和这个女人
for if we do not,
不然的话
our enemies will call us polygamists and drive us off!
我们敌人会指控我们淫乱 消灭我们
Your enemies mean to drive you off in any case, Maddy, and...
你们的敌人无论如何都想消灭你们的 玛蒂 也...
not for a kiss in the night.
不是为黑夜里一个吻吧
Because you tell them to love their fellow men
因为你告诉他们要爱同胞
more than money or land!
更甚于爱钱财和土地
Was it not love that brought you together? Then...
不就是爱把你们联结在一起吗? 那么...
No more, madam. You must both be gone tomorrow.
别说了 夫人 你们明天都得走
We will be gone. Fear not.
我们会走的 别担心
But I leave you with one question.
可我留给你们一个问题
If all on earth are equal,
如果世人皆平等
why do the women work in the fields in the day
为什么女人白天下地干活
and make the men's dinners at night?
晚上还要给男人做饭?
Sometimes we see what's not there.
有时候我们会看见不存在的东西
We see demons of our own conjuring.
我们会看见自己的心魔
I demand the release of my husband, John Lilburne!
我要求释放我丈夫 约翰·李尔本
Why do you sit here with your bellies full
你们怎么能坐在这里享清福
while famine grips the city?!
眼睁睁看着全城挨饿?
No women in this chamber!
本会堂不许妇人出入
Why is the Army forced to Ireland!?
为什么逼军队开去爱尔兰?
We have no fights in Ireland!
我们和爱尔兰没有争执
Get you home and wash dishes.
回家洗碗去吧
They are sold to feed my children!
碗都卖掉给孩子买粮食了
Leave her.
放开她
John will have a fair trial, on my word.
约翰会得到公正的审判 我保证
Sir...
先生...
If you take away John's life,
如果你夺走约翰的生命
I will have yours!
我也会夺走你的
Will they hang you today, John?
他们今天要绞死你吗 约翰?
Hang me? Ask my wife if they will hang me!
绞死我? 问问我老婆 会不会绞死我
I have spent nine shillings on a new pair of boots!
我花9先令买了双新靴子
New boots! See?
新靴子 看到了吧
New boots!
新靴子
John Lilburne.
约翰·李尔本
Where is he? Let me shake his hand.
他在哪里? 我要与他握手
Do you say you are not John Lilburne?
你说你不是约翰·李尔本?
Why should I say I am John Lilburne
我为什么要自称约翰·李尔本
when 'tis said you will hang him for treason?
你不是要以叛国罪绞死他吗?
I say nothing on the matter.
我对此无可奉告
You are charged with being the author of these pamphlets,
你被控撰写这些小册子
which urge the Army to seditious mutiny.
煽动军队发动兵变
How me, sir?
为什么是我 先生?
For that it says the name "John Lilburne" upon them.
因为上面写着"约翰·李尔本"的名字
Why, any man may write "John Lilburne."
那又如何 任何人都可以署名"约翰·李尔本"
Do you deny being the author of these pamphlets?
你否认自己是这些小册子的作者?
What need I deny it when I have not said that I am John Lilburne?
既然我没自称约翰·李尔本 何需否认呢?
And where is the man can prove a single soldier mutinied
企图仅凭这几本小册子
on account of these pamphlets, in any case?
就证明我煽动兵变的人何在?
Where are your witnesses?
你的证人何在?
All in Ireland!
都在爱尔兰
I prithee, let me see the charges
我恳求让我知道罪名
and have time to study the case!
并给予我研究案卷的时间
Sir, you mock this court!
先生 你藐视法庭
No, sir! You mock this court,
不 先生你藐视法庭
as you mock justice, as you mock truth and liberty!
藐视公正 藐视真相和自由
But they will not be mocked forever,
但它们不会一直被轻视
in the name of Almighty God in heaven!
以全能的主之名
Ah, now I remember me you!
现在我记起你了
Were not you, sir, and you, sir,
先生你 还有先生你
and yes, you, sir, all on the King's side
是的 先生你 当初争执开始时
when first we began our quarrel?
你们不是都在国王一方?
Until, as I remember,
据我记忆
until Oliver's Army began to turn the tide when
直到奥利佛的军队开始占上风...
God's amazement - you found yourselves coming over.
上帝呀 你们居然弃暗投明了
Whereas John Lilburne, wherever he may be,
然而无论现在约翰·李尔本在哪里
did fight at Kineton and at Newbury and at Marston Field!
他当初却在金内顿 纽伯里 马斯敦战斗
My bladder is swollen, sir. May I go out to relieve myself?
我的膀胱要憋爆了 先生 能让我去解决一下吗?
No, sir.
不行 先生
Then bring me a pot to piss in!
那么给我一个罐子撒尿
Sirrahs...
小子
I am Honest John Lilburne, author of the pamphlets
我是正直的约翰·李尔本 小册子的作者
that urge the army to resist
煽动军队抵制
an unlawful and barbaric war in Ireland.
在爱尔兰进行的残暴的非法战争
And you, my fellow citizens,
而你们 我的市民同伴们
are the only judges that matter in this place.
是这里唯一有权评判的人
You, and you alone, have the decision.
你们 只有你们能作出判决
My life is in your hands.
我的性命交予你们手中
Men of the jury, what is your verdict?
陪审团 你们有判决了吗?
We have found John Lilburne...
我们裁定约翰·李尔本...
..not guilty.
无罪
I am glad to see you alive.
真高兴看到你还活着
"Glad?"
"高兴"?
Who is he?
他是谁?
A friend.
一个朋友
I never misled you, Sexby.
我从未误导过你 塞斯比
You asked for no love, nor marriage bed,
你说你不祈求爱情或同床共枕
and my heart promised you neither.
而我的心也未曾允诺过你
Aye, but madam,
是的 但夫人
I never thought you would dishonour me before all eyes.
我从未想过你会当着众人的面侮辱我
You are not dishonoured,
你没什么好丢脸的
save your taking part in Irish massacres.
除了你参加的爱尔兰大屠杀
I thought of you every minute.
我无时无刻不在想你
While you slaughtered other men's wives and children?
在你屠戮他人妻儿的时候?
What now?
现在怎么样?
I am your wife.
我是你的妻子
I am yours to command.
一切听凭你的命令
I do not command.
我没有命令
You must go wherever your heart inclines you.
你要跟随心之所向而行
Then fare you well.
那么 再会了
Wait.
等等
I command.
我命令你
What is your future? More soldiering?
你的将来如何打算? 继续军旅生涯吗?
I am a spoiled soldier...
我已经不能再作士兵了
..for which I am glad.
我很庆幸这点
For truly, I have seen my fill of butchering in this vile world.
我在这邪恶的世上看的杀戮已经够了
The world is not vile...
这个世界并不邪恶...
..though some are that are in it.
尽管有一些邪恶的人存在
Even they can be saved by love, I think.
我觉得即使是他们 也能被爱拯救
Love?
爱?
Aye, love.
是的 爱
I think you do not know it.
我觉得你不懂
And I pity you for it.
我可怜你
Did love help the Diggers
当军队践踏掘地者的土地时
when the army trampled their fields?
爱有助他们一臂之力吗?
No.
没有
What did love do for any man,
爱究竟与人何用
except make him run like a fool to his destruction?
除了驱使人傻乎乎地奔向毁灭?
The Diggers had not too much love, sir, but too little.
掘地者的爱不是太多了 先生 而是太少
But there are those who believe that love can save us all.
但仍有人坚信爱能拯救我们所有人
Ranters?
喧嚣者派?(另一无政府主义团体)
Only their enemies call them that.
只有他们的敌人那样叫
They call themselves the High Attainers,
他们自称进取派
and I have made friends amongst them.
我在他们当中结交了不少朋友
Ranters?!
喧嚣者中?
Sir, you are drunk.
先生 你醉了
Madam, do you know where this "love" will bring you?
夫人 你知道"爱"会将你带向何方吗?
Do you know they have made female adultery a capital offence?
你知道他们将女性的通奸定为死罪吗?
If you continue as you are, they will hang you again.
如果你秉性不改 他们会再次绞死你
Who will save you? That boy?
谁会救你? 那个男孩?
That "boy", sir,
先生 那个"男孩"
may not know how to split a man open with his sword,
也许不懂得怎么用剑杀人
but he sees the truth in us.
但他能看到我们的内在
In who? In me?
谁的内在? 我的?
In me.
我的
In us all. He sees love shining in our hearts,
我们所有人的 他看到我们心中有爱
and he sees what it can do here, on earth.
他看到这样的爱能在世上有何作为
Sexby, what use to bring down kings or parcel out land,
塞斯比 就算我们推翻国王 分掉土地
if we do not share all that is in us?
如果不能推倒心防 又有何用?
Madam...do you lie with him?
夫人...你和他上床吗?
Like all men, you are a fool when you drink.
你跟所有男人一样 喝多了就变蠢货
Do you lie with him? Have you lain with him?
你和他睡了吗? 你和他睡过了?
Let me go from here, sir.
让我离开这里 先生
Where to?
去哪里?
To him?
去他那儿?
Oh, he "loves" you. He loves your innards,
噢 他"爱"你 他爱你的内在
where the light does shine, whereas I...
爱你内心的光芒 但是我...
Sexby, I can never love you.
塞斯比 我永远不可能爱上你
Ever.
永不
I am sorry for you.
我怜悯你
I am grateful to you.
我感激你
But I will never love you.
但我不会爱上你
Why do you stop, sir? The law says you own me.
还犹豫什么 先生? 法律说我归你了
Live as you please. You are free.
随自己的意愿过活吧 你自由了
But there is no freedom.
但世上的自由
Except that which comes with money and power.
只可能由金钱和权力而来
If you know of any other kind, then...
如果你发现别种自由 那么...
..you must run after it.
你一定要好好追求
Go.
走吧
GO!
走
Where is Christian?
克里斯廷呢?
She must not escape a third time.
不能让她逃走第三次了
She'll not, sir.
她逃不掉的 先生
I've led her by the nose like a willing sow.
她像母猪一样被我牵着鼻子
And she truly believed The Diggers
她真的相信掘地者了?
Yes,sir.She gave her heart to fools and thieves.
对 先生 她真心相信那帮愚人和小偷
And now?
现在呢?
Now she believes the world she longs for is finally at hand.
现在她相信她终于得到了自己渴望的世界
It is.
的确是的
Sir, may your victory be the vanguard of ours.
先生 愿你的胜利成为我们的前锋
'Your release the harbinger of freedom for all on Earth.'
你为全世界释放自由的先兆
The perfect freedom of universal love.
博爱的真正自由
Universal love?
博爱?
Universal love.
博爱